早く早く
Hurry!
やばい   緊張する
Gosh, I'm so nervous...
来た
Here it comes!
金だ
Gold!
金だよ私たち
We got gold!
私アサミに報告してくる
I'm going to go tell Asami.
あの子緊張でトイレに閉じこもってるから
She's so nervous, she's hiding in the washroom.
この中より   関西大会に出場する学…
The following schools will compete in the Kansai Competition.
金だ…
Gold...
ダメ金だけど   金
We got dud gold, but still gold.
高坂さん   泣くほど嬉しかったんだ
You're happy enough to cry, huh?
よかったね   金賞で
Congratulations, we got gold.
悔しい   悔しくって死にそう
I'm so upset, I could die.
何でみんなダメ金なんかで喜べるの
Why are people happy, when we didn't even make it?
私ら全国目指してたんじゃないの？
Weren't we shooting for the Nationals?
本気で全国行けると思ってたの？
Did you really think we could make the Nationals?
あんたは悔しくないわけ？
Aren't you upset?
私は悔しい   めちゃくちゃ悔しい
I'm totally upset!
高校に入ったら   胸が大きくなるなんて噂
Why did I believe the rumor that my breasts would get bigger,
どうして信じちゃったんだろう
once I was in high school?
行ってきます
I'm off.
行ってらしゃい
Take care.
そんなことを思いつつ   私の高校生活は始まろうとしていた
that was the kind of thing
I was thinking about.
わざわざ同じ中学の子が少ないこの学校を選んだのは
Although there weren't many people from my middle school here,
憧れのセーラー服の高校がここだけだったのと
this school was the only one with the sailor-style uniforms I'd always liked,
いろんなことを一度リセットしたかったから
and because, in a lot of ways,
I wanted a fresh start.
新入生の皆さん   北宇治高校へようこそ
Welcome to Kitauji High School.
吹部だ
It's the concert band.
輝かしい皆さんの入学を祝して
To celebrate your admittance...
ダメだこりゃ
They're hopeless.
叶えたい事が溢れてるから
立ち止まってる暇なんてないよね
胸に秘めたあこがれを   フルボリュームで届けよう
行こう   クレシェンドの向こうへ
つまずいてもいい   はみだしてもいい
君の音色を   僕たちは待っている
響け   生まれたての夢つめ込んで
大きな空へ   今旅立とう
拓け   笑顔を味方につけて
離さない   諦めたくない
限界さえも   跳ね返す勇気で
DREAM   SOLISTER
下手すぎる
They suck!
バラバラしてた   ピッチも合ってないし   リズムも
They're off-pitch and out of rhythm.
でも   まあ   全国目指してる感じじゃないんだよな
But well, I guess they aren't trying for Nationals...
でも   あれは下手だよな
But they really sucked.
何が？
What sucked?
今は言ってたじゃん
You said, "They really sucked."
下手だよなぁって
声に出てた   ていうか
Did I say that out loud?
あなたは？
Who are you?
あたし？   加藤葉月
Hazuki Katou!
後ろの席だから   よろしく
I sit behind you. Nice to meet you.
私   黄前久美子   よろしく
I'm Kumiko Oumae.
で   何が…
So, what-
席に着け
Take your seats!
高校生にもなって
You're in high school now.
You shouldn't make noise in class.
教室で馬鹿騒ぎするというのはあまり褒められたものではないな
I'm unimpressed.
何だそのスカート丈は
Explain the length of your skirts.
すぐ直せ
Fix them now.
すみません
Sorry.
私はこの一年三組を担任する松本美知恵だ
I'll be in charge of class 1-3.
まずは名前を確認する
First, I'll call the roll.
浅井ゆうだい
Yuudai Asai.
はい
Here.
石川ゆき
Yuki Ishikawa.
はい
Here.
内山田ひろこ
Hiroko Uchiyamada.
はい
Here.
江口ようこ
Yoko Eguchi.
はい
Here.
黄前久美子
Kumiko Oumae.
はい
Here.
加藤葉月
Hazuki Katou.
はい
Here.
川島…りょく…き？
Kawashima?
すみません   あの…それサファイアです
Sorry, it's "Sapphire."
緑が輝くと書いてサファイアです
Written as "green" and "shining."
川島サファイア
Sapphire Kawashima...
サファイアか   かっこいいね
Sapphire, huh?
すまない   もう間違わない
That sounds awesome.
いいえ
It's fine.
久美子   一緒に帰ろ？
Kumiko, let's walk home together.
久美子？
Huh? "Kumiko"?
合ってるよね   名前
Yeah, isn't that your name?
それは合ってる
Yeah, it is.
よね
Right?
私葉月ね   加藤とかでもいいよ   適当に読んで
I'm Hazuki!
一緒に帰る子いないの？
Don't you walk home with anyone else?
いや   あたしさ   高校で新しい友達作って
I decided I'm going to make new friends in high school
新しいこといっぱいするって決めてるんだ
and do all kinds of new things.
だからよろしくね   久美子ちゃん
I'm counting on you, Kumiko-chan!
で   何が下手だったの
So what sucked?
それはもういいじゃん
Let's just forget that.
あ   オパールちゃん
Opal-chan!
違うよ   なんかもっと緑色っぽい…
No, it's something greener.
あの   あのあの   それってチューバくんですよね
Hey, isn't that Tuba-kun?
かわいいな   チュウバくん   大好きなんです
It's so cute, Tuba-kun.
触ってもいい…
- Could I touch-
- Hey, Opal-chan.
ねぇ   オパールちゃん
- Could I touch-
- Hey, Opal-chan.
サファイアです
It's "Sapphire."
あ   ごめん   サファイアちゃん
Oh, sorry. Sapphire-chan...
好きなんだ
You like it?
はい   かわいいなー
Yes! It's so cute...
何それ
What is it?
チュウバのゆるキャラだよ
It's a tuba mascot character.
チュウバ？
Tuba?
金管の楽器？
A brass instrument?
緑吹部だったんですよ   コンバスやってました
Midori was in the concert band, on contrabass.
コンバス？   緑？
Contrabass?
緑というのは緑の名前です
Midori is my name.
サファイアって   なんかあれですし
You know, the name "Sapphire" is kind of...
緑って呼んでいただけるとありがたいなって思ってます
I'd appreciate if you'd call me "Midori."
そして   コンバスというのは楽器の名前です
And "contrabass" is the name of an instrument.
こーんな大きなバイオリンのお化けみたいなやつです
It's like a freakish violin.
知ってますか
Have you seen one?
それ見たことあるよ
I've seen one.
ありますか
You have?
私も吹部だったよ
I was in concert band, too.
本当ですか   えーっと
Um...
黄前久美子   久美子でいいよ
Call her "Kumiko."
私は葉月ね   よろしく
I'm Hazuki. Nice to meet you.
アイ   コピー
Copy.
久美子ちゃんは
What about you?
久美子ちゃんのパートは？
What part did you play?
あ   低音   ユーフォやってたよ
I used to play euph.
なるほど   ぽいですね
Yeah, I can see that.
ユーフォ？
H-Huh? UFO?
ユーフォじゃなくてユーフォ
Not "UFO." It's "euph."
ユーフォニアムっていう…あ   これの小さいの
It's called a euphonium.
えー   だいぶちっちゃいね
Yeah? That's really small.
私ね   中学まではテニス部だったんだけど
Until now, I've been in the tennis club.
高校からは吹奏楽やろうと思ってるんだ
But with high school,
I might join the concert band.
え   嘘   緑今から吹部の見学へ行くんです
I was about to go watch the concert band.
もしよかったら   みんなで一緒に行きませんか
How about we all go together?
わーすごっ   あれトランペットだよね
That's a trumpet, isn't it?
私   あれがいいんだ
I like those.
かっこいいよね
They look awesome!
見て見て葉月ちゃん   あれがユーフォ
Look, Hazuki-chan. That's a euph.
どれどれ   ユーフォデカッ
Huh, UFOs are huge!
もう   びっくりするじゃん
Jeez, you surprised me, Kumiko.
You said it was smaller than Tuba-kun...
久美子がチュウバくんよりちっちゃいって言うから
Jeez, you surprised me, Kumiko.
You said it was smaller than Tuba-kun...
あ   ごめん
Oh, sorry.
サックスもいいなぁ
Sax is nice, too!
葉月ちゃん   痛い
H-Hazuki-chan...
大丈夫？
Are you all right?
あれー   君達   もしかして見学しに来てくれたのかな
Are you here to watch?
さ   入って入って
Then, come in.
Come   on   join   us
Come on, join us!
やばっ   きれい
she's pretty!
さささ   これが我が校の吹奏楽部です
Now, this is our school band.
君達が見学者第一号   記念に飴をあげちゃおう
You're the first visitors.
どうも   すみません
Thank you.
え？
Huh?
パー
Asuka...
あすか
はい？
Yes?
新入生が緊張するから
We agreed not to talk to the new students too much,
あんまり話しかけないようにしよって決めたでしょ
so we don't scare them, remember?
え？
Huh?
さっそく怯えてるよ
They're already terrified.
ごめんね   ゆっくり見ていってね
Sorry, make yourselves at home.
よろしく
Nice to meet you!
ほら   行くよ
Come on, let's go.
銅賞…
Bronze prize.
ね   久美子   あの四角いの何？
Hey, what's that square thing?
あ   チューナーだよ   あれで音を合わせるの
You tune against it.
あれー   もしかして君初心者？
Oh? Are you a beginner?
あ   はい
Yes.
そっかそっか   じゃあ   吹奏楽の基本的なことから教えてあげよ…
Then I'll teach you the basics of brass.
あーすーか
はいはい
Fine, fine.
じゃあ   チューニングベーで
A tuning B-flat, please.
トロンボーン   ちゃんと狙って
Trombone, place your note.
ホルン   ずれてるよ   ちゃんと音聴いて
Horn, you're off. Listen carefully.
もっかいやろっか
Let's do it again.
チューナーを使っていいから
You can use your tuner.
何
What?
ちょっと音が合ってなくて
They were a bit off.
そうなの
Really?
高坂さん？
Kousaka-san?
すみません
Excuse me.
見学ですか
Are you here to visit?
いえ   入部したいんですけど
No, I'd like to join.
本当？
Really?
ようこそ   吹奏楽部へ
Welcome to the concert band!
梨子   早く入部届け
Hurry, register her for the club!
今ですか？
Now?
当たり前でしょ   逃げちゃったらどうすんの
What if she runs away?
そんな   ネコじゃあるまいし   そろそろ行きましょうか
She isn't a cat or anything.
失礼しました
Thank you!
さっきの子   綺麗でしたね
That girl was pretty.
知り合いですか
Do you know her?
知り合いっていうか   中学の時   吹部で一緒だったんだけど
I was with her in the middle school band.
知り合いじゃん
Then you know her.
すごくってわけじゃなくて
Not too well.
そんなもん
That's it, huh?
でも   この学校の吹部って思ってた以上に…その…
But the band here wasn't, uh...
久美子すごっ
うまくないよね
...as good as I expected.
そうなの
Really?
そうですね
That's right...
たぶん府大会では「目指せ銀賞」なんじゃないかな
They're probably aiming for a Prefectural silver.
銀賞だったらすごいんじゃないの
Silver would be pretty good, wouldn't it?
関西とか   まあ   全国とかに行きたかったら
If we wanted to go to the Kansai
Competition or to the Nationals,
各大会で金賞を取らなくてはいけないんです
we'd have to get gold in each competition.
しかも金賞といっても   ダメ金ではいけません
And it can't be a dud gold.
It has to be a proper gold.
ダメ…ダメ金って   なに
Dud what? What's dud gold mean?
吹奏楽のコンクールは   金   銀   銅の3つの賞があって
Band competitions have gold, silver, and bronze prizes.
金賞の中から   代表が選ばれるんだけど
Representatives are chosen from the gold-prize winners,
選ばなかった金をダメ金っていうの
and the ones not chosen are called "dud golds."
緑輝ちゃんが言うみたいに      次の大会に進みたかったらダメ金じゃダメで…
Like Sapphire-chan said, if you want to move on to the next competition,
難しかった？
Was that complicated?
うん
Yeah.
ごめん
Sorry.
でもさ   3人が入部すれば救世主になれるんじゃない
But maybe if the three of us join, we can be their saviors.
そんな簡単じゃないよ
It isn't that simple.
そう？
No?
緑はやりますよ   音楽が好きですから
I love music.
音楽はいつだって
Music speaks to people's hearts, all throughout the world.
世界中の人々の心に訴えることができる強力な言語の1つだって信じてるので
信号   なかなか変わらないね
The signal isn't changing, is it?
緑   ボタン押し忘れていました
I forgot to press the button!
頼むよ   緑輝ちゃん
Come on, Sapphire-chan...
緑です
It's "Midori."
久美子は
How about you, Kumiko?
どうする   吹部
The band?
私？   私は…
I'm...
ちょっと考える
I'm not sure.
電車が来ました   私   こっちなので
I'm going this way.
じゃね
Bye.
また明日ね
See you tomorrow.
わかった
Oh, I get it now.
下手って言ってたの   吹部のことだ
When you said they sucked, you meant the band.
なんでだろう
Why?
高坂さんがいた
Kousaka-san was there...
うまいから   洛秋とか立華とかに行ってると思ってた
I thought she'd be at Rakushu or Rikka or somewhere.
抜かった
Damn it...
何を
What?
よっ
Hey.
秀一か
Oh, Shuichi.
あれ
Huh?
おい   幼馴染にあいさつ無しですか
We've known each other since we were little. At least say hi.
同じ学校だというのに
We're in the same school.
髪   縛ってんの
You're tying your hair back?
だねー
I guess...
そういや   高坂麗奈いたな   全然知らなかった
Oh yeah, I saw Reina Kousaka.
ていうか   反応   鈍くないか
Though, aren't you a bit slow?
話しかけてくんなっていうから   従ってるんですよ
You told me not to talk to you, so I'm not talking to you.
はい？
Huh?
「しゃべってくんな   ブース」って言ったじゃん   中3の時
In the third year of junior high, you said, "Quit talking to me, ugly."
あれはお前がみんなの前で
Oh, that was because you asked me,
「今日うちでご飯食べんの」とか聞いてくるから
"Are you eating at my place tonight?" in front of others.
違った   今それどころじゃなかったんだ
That's not right, and I don't really have time for this.
おい
Hey.
ごめん   帰るわ
Sorry, I'm going home.
お前さ   部活   どうすんの
Hey, what are you doing about clubs?
まだ   決めてないよ
I haven't decided yet.
吹部じゃねえの
Not band?
あんたは   俺？
What about you?
俺はまあ   ほかにやりたいこともないし
Well, it isn't like there's anything else I want to do.
吹部かな
Band, I guess...
そっか
Oh.
私は…
I'm...
入らない
I'm not joining.
入ろうと思ってたけど   やめることにした
I was thinking of joining, but I decided not to.
なんでも   じゃあね
Because.
なんだよ
What the...
ただいまー
I'm home.
あら   おかえり   高校どうだった
How was high school?
まあまあ
Hmm... Meh.
お姉ちゃん   帰ってきてるわよ
Your sister's home.
そう
Yeah?
ご飯の支度   手伝って
Help me fix dinner.
はーい
Okay.
吹部なぁ…
Band, huh?
本気で全国行けると思ってたの
Did you really think we could make the Nationals?
悪気があったわけじゃないんです
I didn't mean that in a bad way.
ただ思ったことが   うっかり口に出てしまったというか
I just kind of blurted out what I was thinking.
金取れたし   いいじゃん   みたいなところもあって
And I was sort of happy that we got gold...
ダメ金でも   立派な金
Dud gold is still a gold-
なにやってんの
What are you doing?
やあ   ポニーテールなんてしちゃって   初日から気合入れすぎ
You even wore a ponytail.
うるさいなぁ   ってか   勝手に開けないでよ
And don't open the door without asking.
はいはい   すまん   すまん
Sorry.
そういえばさ
Oh, yeah.
だから   勝手に開けないで
I said, "Don't open it"!
あんた   吹奏楽   やめるの
Are you quitting concert band?
なんで
Why?
北宇治だから
Because you're at Kitauji.
やめる…か？
Quitting, huh?
見せて見せて
Let me see!
末吉と吉って   どっちがいいの
Which is supposed to be better luck, sue-kichi or kichi?
末吉なんじゃない
I think it's sue-kichi.
上から   大吉   中吉   小吉   吉   半吉   末吉   末小吉ですね
han-kichi, sue-kichi, sue-shou-kichi.
つまり   吉のほうが上です
So kichi is better.
ど…どうも
Th-Thanks.
そうなんですね
I see.
私も久しぶりにおみくじを引いてみたくなりました
Now I feel like getting a fortune, too.
おっと
Ah, whoops.
しまった
Shoot.
失礼
Excuse me.
すみません
Sorry.
運動会だ
Sports festival?
「天国と地獄」だっけ
Heaven and Hell, was it?
正しくは「地獄のオルフェ」です
Actually, Orpheus in the Underworld.
とてもいい曲ですよ
It's a very nice piece.
では
Well, then.
ご飯は
Are you eating?
いい
No.
出ないよ
It isn't working...
え？どうしたの   それ？
Where did you get that?
買ったの？
I bought it.
買った   買っちゃったの？
Bought it? You actually bought it?
これだけね
Yeah, just this.
気が早すぎるよ   楽器もまだ決まってないのに
You haven't even chosen an instrument...
どうやって鳴らすんです？
How do you play it?
緑はコンバスだったので   教えてください
I used to play contrabass.
えっと…
Um...
唇を…
Your lips.
唇をこうやって震わせるんだよ
Make your lips vibrate, like this.
って   やってみな
Try it.
で   それをマウスピースでやってみ
Now try it with the mouthpiece.
いいじゃん
Not bad.
出た
It worked!
出たよね   今
It worked, right?
出た   音出た
It worked! I made a sound!
どうやったんです？
How did you do it?
わかんない
I don't know!
そうそう   久美子ちゃん
Oh, Kumiko-chan...
吹部   一緒に入りませんか
Do you want to join the concert band with us?
本当
Really?
やった
Yay.
こうして   私は   北宇治高校吹奏楽部に入部した
And so, I joined the Kitauji
High School Concert Band.
そして   次の曲が始まるのです
And now, the next piece begins.
トゥッティ!   私たちが心を奪う
マウスピースと今日のリードを選びながら
汚れたクロスが匂う
書き込んだスコアたちが試してるの
青春の価値
奏でる   教室の窓から
繋げる   フレーズからフレーズへ
ひとりでも   欠けたらダメなんだ
音に伝わる感動   みんなで響け!
体が歌ってる   煌めきのパッセージ
チューナーの揺らぎはきっと   舞い上がる高揚感
想いを乗せてゆく   楽器って赤い糸
息を合わせて…
トゥッティ!   私たちが心を奪う